Right.
I'll just let a couple more people join.
Alrighty.
Good morning everyone. Thank you for
joining us today. I hope you all had a
good holiday season. This meeting is for
the patient qualification and safety
committee. Let me go ahead and bring up
my presentation.
If my computer would like to
not wanting to let me
share. Is there any way you can?
>> Yes, I will bring it on up. Give me just
a moment.
>> Okay. Should be able to see the screen.
>> Yes.
Alrighty. So, uh again, good morning
everyone. Today's meeting is both an
orientation um and just kind of the
first formal meeting for this committee.
We're going to walk through this
committee's authority, scope,
expectations, and initial work. And
you'll have the opportunity to decide
whether you wish to participate.
Uh next slide.
Perfect. Um, thank you all for taking
the time to be here. I want to be clear
at the outset. Um, attendance today does
not obligate you to serve. This meeting
is designed to give you information you
need to make an informed decision about
participation. For those who choose to
participate in today's meetings, this
will form the basis of the initial
committee and operation.
Um, next.
Cool. All right. So today's objective is
pretty simple, pretty straightforward.
First, we will explain the authority,
scope, and responsibilities of this
committee. Second, we will review and
vote on um
the committee bylaws and the initial
qualifying conditions that were passed
by the legislature.
Third, we want to create space for
questions, discussions, um and informed
consent. That way, everyone knows, you
know, what we're doing here, what we're
participating in, and what we're kind of
building together. Um, next slide.
Perfect. So, advisory committees are um
they exist to bring expertise and lived
experience into policy development. This
structure allows individuals to
contribute meaningfully even if they
cannot choose even if they cannot or
choose not to serve directly on the
board due to real or perceived conflicts
of interest. committee strengthened the
board's work by broadening input,
grounding recommendations and evidence,
and ensuring diverse perspectives are
represented.
Next,
so it's important to define the
committee's authority. So the committee
serves in an advisory capacity to the
medical psilocybin advisory board. This
meeting functions as an initial um
meeting for the patient qualification
and safety committee. participation is
voluntary and does not obligate service
and um the authorities of this committee
are to recommend it does not regulate.
We provide clinical safety and policy
guidance but final decisions rest with
the medical psilocybin advisory board
and the department of health. This
distinction protects both the committee
and its members while ensuring
recommendations remain evidence-based
and transparent.
Next slide.
Perfect. And then the patient
qualification and safety committee
exists to um recommend to the board
qualifying conditions and clinical
indications for medical psilocybin
services. We recommend to the board
safety, stability and exclusion
criteria. And we review and evaluate
petitions for recommendations to the
board to add new qualifying conditions,
modify existing qualifying conditions,
add, revise or remove contraindications
or exclusions. So I do want to add an
important note. Um if you just decide to
serve on this committee, it does not
prohibit you from serving on another in
the U medical psilocybin program. The
patient qualification and safety
committee focuses on one core mission
protecting patient safety while ensuring
appropriate access. So as long as we can
maintain those, we don't mind um sharing
expertise with other committees.
Next.
All right. So uh just absolutely clear
we want to make sure that committee
service is known to be voluntary
advisory and collaborative. Um we enjoy
and learn from the clinical experience,
scientific knowledge and lived
experience um from our members and we
value respectful disagreement,
evidence-driven discussion and clear
documentation of recommendation.
Uh next.
And so um now if you wish to uh serve
and help us out on this uh committee,
we'll open the floor to introductions if
you wish to be considered for this um
committee.
Briefly share your name, area of ent
area of expertise, sorry, and your
interest in patient qualification and
safety.
If you would like to speak, um, please
raise your hand.
Perfect.
All right, I will go ahead and recognize
James Brown first.
>> Morning everyone. Thank you for your
time and for this uh participation. I
really wish everybody had a happy New
Year's. Um Ian and Dominic and
everybody, thank you so much again. Uh
my name is James Brown and I'm a doctor
of pharmacy from the University of New
Mexico. Um I've been a very um big
advocate of this um from the beginning.
Um so my expertise really would be um
I'm psilocybin trained um from Oregon as
a facilitator. So I went through a
program up there in Oregon. So, I'm very
familiar with the laws, bylaws,
patient, uh, precipitation,
um, qualifications. Um, you know, being
a pharmacist, I know everything about
contraindications, disease state, drug
interactions, all that stuff. Um, safety
is right up my alley. Um, I'm a veteran,
um, who is disabled.
So, um, you know, that's that's where
kind of where I'm sitting, um, as a vet,
disabled. Um, I'm I'm liking to
represent some of that patient
population. Um,
that's but that's, you know, Ian and
Dominic, that's who I am. Um, I would
love to send you guys my resume if you
guys need to see that. Um,
I'll go from there. Thank you so much.
>> Thank you so much, James. Um, we
appreciate your expertise and your
participation. I will now hear from
Katherine. Oh, sorry. Tara Lipo,
just to inform me to unmute, uh, if
you've been given the right to unmute,
you have to manually unmute yourself. If
you could please click on the mic button
to unmute yourself. Thank you.
All right. Um,
yes, Tara, you have been unmuted on our
end. Uh, if you just click on the unmute
button, uh, if you're on a computer,
it'll be in the upper right of, uh, the
computer, you should be able to speak at
this time.
No worries, Tara. Um, what we can go
ahead and do is if you want to leave and
rejoin, we can go ahead and see if that
fixes things. Sometimes computers just
need to be restarted. And then I'll go
ahead and go to Katherine Waro while
we're waiting for her to rejoin.
>> Good morning, everybody. um really
appreciate that we get to organize and
do this. Um I am a licensed professional
counselor in Los Cusus, New Mexico. I
have been trained by Therosel up in
Canada and I've been pretty much doing
this work for about 3 years now. Um, and
I even have um an entire assessment I
use with clients to make sure that one
um that this medicine works for them.
Um, also to remove any contraindications
or um any situations uh that would be
unsafe. So I I have experience. I have
hands-on experience um and I feel like I
can contribute in that way. Um I safety
is very important to me. It's always
been important to me. I try to follow as
much as possible the clinical studies um
that have been you know and the research
I follow research um and what's been
published as much as possible. And um I
also um
not sure how all of you are familiar
with www. psychedelic.com.
Kristen Spears, a pharmacist up in uh
Colorado that has developed a website
that allows you to put all your
medications in and see what might uh you
know what what needs to happen around
psilocybin
um with any medications and I've been um
requiring clients do that. So I have
some experience. I'm definitely not a
pharmacist um but I I do have quite a
bit of um knowledge and experience that
I would like to contribute. Thank you.
Thank you.
All right.
Oh, sorry. Gone, Dominic.
>> I was just going to say it looks like
Tara has rejoined and I have unmuted
her. Um, Tara, if you want to try to
unmute.
Okay. Uh, it looks like we're still not
able to hear Tara, so we'll have to come
on back. So, Ian, I would go on ahead to
the next individual.
>> Uh, Kate Hawk.
>> Hi, everybody. Yeah, my name's Kate
Hawk. I'm in Santa Fe and uh I've been
involved with psychedelics
professionally for quite a while. I've
been a MAPS member since the 1980s. I've
been a trauma therapist since all that
time as well. I've worked with on the
Navajo Nation in Arizona before moving
to New Mexico. And also have a range of
experience from doing harm reduction at
Burning Man. I've been a ketamine
assisted therapist for quite a while.
I've done the Colorado natural medicine
uh facilitator training there and um my
focus these days is death and
psychedelics
uh especially uh with end of life. So
I'll be actively involved with the end
of life committee but I'm also very
interested in safety feel like balancing
safety and access is success uh
essential you know to the success of
what we're doing and we have quite a an
opportunity to be a model u a lot of
different states are looking at us so
I'm happy to contribute and uh that's an
introduction I really appreciate how
this whole process has been focused as
well is inviting uh people's
participation. So, and Ian, you're just
doing an incredible job, Dominic. I just
I'm not used to feeling so confident in
uh government and regulation, but I
really really appreciate how well this
is being done. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
All right. Uh, Ann Mitz
Oh,
>> no worries. And we can go to uh Gregory
Evans while we're waiting for her to
rejoin
>> if we do have more issues um with people
joining and you're just unable to speak.
Dominic put it in the chat, but you can
go ahead and just leave your
introduction there. Still going to look
over it. I'm not going to blame you for
technical difficulties. That's not your
fault. Um, but yeah, we can I will still
accept your introduction. Still happy to
meet you even if it has to be through
chat, but I will yield to Gregory Evans.
>> Thank you. Is my mic working?
>> Excellent.
>> You are. Thank you. You are, Greg.
>> Uh, good to see everybody.
What a day. The first committee.
Um I my personal position is coming from
an independent researcher um stance. I
have become very very interested in
um
genetics analytics of uh biomass and the
way that behaves with people um and
analyzing
dosage and practice and protocol and all
of the things that come around like harm
reduction and proper usage. And proper I
mean like that could be like let's put
all the definitions down of what proper
could be. Um as far as patient
qualification and safety I just want to
be a part of the peanut gallery here. I
have plans to primary primarily
contribute to uh research and continuous
improvement dosage administration and
clinical practice propagation committee
propagation committees. Um, but I think
all of those things kind of weave
together and I'm happy to be a vessel to
transfer information around the larger
ecosystem and make sure that you know
like as we get into propagation part of
the compliance measures force for
testing that feed into dosage
administration and applications for for
patients with specific qualifications
and such. So, I'm just here as like a
research nerd that probably has too much
information to share
and I yield.
>> We appreciate all research. Um, as a bit
of a research nerd myself, I happy to
have you. I will now yield to James. I'm
going to mess this up. Hos.
>> Thanks, Ian. Yes, my name is James Hosov
and um I'm from Arizona
and I'm a pharmaceutical scientist with
a training background in biochemistry
and medicinal and I really focus on
psychoactive substances.
In my uh professional uh realm, I have
uh worked in clinical trial research
operations along with preclinical
environments using animal models and I
feel I have a strong emphasis on patient
protection and protocol fidelity and I
think this committee is absolutely
incredible because in order to obtain
and achieve access we need data and I
think in order to obtain data we have to
have clear safety protocols in line. So
I think that this committee can help
define clear evidence-based
qualifications, exclusion criterium, and
specifically I'm interested in potential
medical and psychiatric risk
stratification along with medication
interactions that can um that you know
potentially could happen when dosing
with psilocybin. So I think that this is
a very important realm that needs to be
uh taken with extreme care and caution
but it's very exciting time. So thank
you very much for listening to what I
have to say and I look forward to
meeting and chatting with everybody.
Thank you so much. Um it looks like we
have
Senator Steinborn next.
>> Indeed. Good morning everybody and I and
thanks for hosting this committee today
and um creating it. I I do not have a
clinical background at all but I'm very
interested in the safety issue. I think
this is this is
probably well one of the most important
if not the most important committee just
to make sure we kind of get it right and
have the right parameters in place. I'm
also interested in
issues of safety even beyond the program
but but in um psilocybin that's out
there and I think there there might be
an appropriate space for the program and
the department of health to to be
putting out some good information to the
public on that. I don't know if that's
appropriate or not but um yeah so I
really um don't know if it's appropriate
or not. just kind of want to be in the
room and be a party to the discussions
and listen and contribute where I might
I'm also trying to pay close attention
to what other states are doing and doing
my own research. So might be additive on
occasion but very very interested in and
uh you know so if if appropriate I'd
love to be in the room and be on the
list serve and and join in on occasion.
Thanks.
>> Of course. We appreciate all input. And
then if Ann got hers working, she is
next.
>> Oh, great. Thanks for your patience. Um,
good morning everyone. It's nice to be
here. I'm Dr. Anne Mets. I'm a licensed
professional counselor here in New
Mexico. Um, I live in TA and I have over
12 years of clinical experience
including extensive work with behavioral
emergencies in emergency room settings.
I currently serve as clinical faculty at
Southern New Hampshire University and as
a clinical facilitator at Numia healing
in Colorado's regulated psilocybin
program. Um my training is in
psychedelic assisted therapy um and it
includes specialized certifications
through fluence for psilocybin and
ketamine assisted psychotherapy. I've
also done the MDMA training for PTSD
through MAPS. Um, my clinical research
and clinical interests center on grief
work and navigating life transitions,
which has really deepened my commitment
to patient safety protocols in
psychedelic medicine. Um, my work in
Colorado's program has shown me what
functions well within a regulatory
structure and where improvements can be
made. So, I'm just here to help New
Mexico build a safety framework that
balances access with clinical rigor um
that ensures both patient safety and
therapeutic efficacy. And I really
appreciate the opportunity to contribute
to the committee.
Thanks.
>> All righty. Well, thank you all for
speaking. If I have no no one else that
would like to um introduce themselves,
we can go ahead and move on to the
adoption of the Bibles.
>> Ian, can we check and see if Tara is
able to unmute her mic on her end now?
>> Yes, Tara, you are good to go. If you
are able to unmute.
Okay, it looks like unfortunately Tara
is not able to join. Our apologies Tara.
Um it does look like it may just be an
issue with your microphone specifically,
but um hopefully you'll be able to
participate through the chat itself. So,
thank you. Back to you.
>> She did she did put in an introduction
in the chat.
>> Perfect.
All righty. Um, so then we can move on
to the adoption of the bylaws.
See if I can get
Would
you mind sharing the bylaws? I don't
know why my computer is being
frustrating. No, not a problem, Ian. I
am just uh trying to pull it up myself.
It is uh running a little bit slow, but
give me just a moment.
There we go.
There we go. All right. Can is that uh
visible now?
>> Yes. Um all righty guys. So we will go
ahead and go through the bylaws. So
these are um very basic kind of
procedural stuff that we have to adopt
as a committee. Um if you have spoken,
you are a member of the committee. you
are um going to be helping us out with
these patient qualification safety
things. Um so if you would like to vote
on it, you are more than welcome. So to
begin with, article one just establishes
patient qualification and safety
committee is our name and we'll refer to
it as the committee in the document
after um its authority. It's operating
under the medical psilocybin advisory
board pursuant to you know applicable
statutes.
The purpose of this committee is to
ensure that psilocybin services in New
Mexico are grounded in scientific
evidence, appropriate safety standards,
and clinically sound patient screening
criteria with the goal of protecting
patient safety while promoting equitable
and effective access to care. Now, we'll
get into the kind of more specific
stuff. If you could scroll down for me,
Dominic. Um,
all right. So, this is going to be what
we're doing. So there are we have to be
responsible for the following
qualification conditions and
indications. This means that um we
review the scientific literature,
clinical data, emerging evidence um and
we recommend to the board qualifying
conditions or symptom clusters that may
benefit from psilocybin services. This
also includes periodically reassessing
existing qualifications in light of new
evidence or safety concerns. As I'm sure
all of the experts on this board know,
to western medicine, this is a very new
topic. So, finding um you know,
applicable evidence and clinical data is
a little bit strenuous, but we will be
using that clinical data to make the
program as safe as it can while still
providing, you know, the appropriate
medications to our patients.
Section 4.2, petitions for modification.
So, these are going to be coming from
the patients. um saying, "Hey, I have
this condition. I think it would benefit
from this." Um they would review and
evaluate petitions to add new qualifying
conditions, modify existing qualifying
conditions, and add, revise, or remove
contraindications or exclusions.
Um this also means applying standardized
criteria for how we're going to review
these petitions um including the
strength of the evidence, the risk
benefit profile, the feasibility and the
equity considerations.
The next thing we have to do is patient
safety and exclusion criteria. We
recommend
um
patient safety standards and exclusion
criteria like medical and psychiatric
red flag conditions, medication
interaction concerns and physiological
and cognitive safety considerations. And
we ensure that the recommended criteria
align with the current clinical best
practices and public health principles.
Um
yes it will
will it be posted Dom?
uh once we are able to post the minutes
um just to let everybody know that um
just due to the because we have to
submit any documents to our IT uh and so
it can take a few business days for
items to be posted but we will go ahead
and submit these along with the minutes
of the meeting um after the comments
have been received. Uh if you look in
the chat, we have asked that individuals
submit their comments by Monday, January
5th. Um if it's possible to do that by
noon and then after that, we'll submit
all of the documents for uh to be
available on the the uh medical
psilocybin advisory board committee's
websites.
>> Perfect.
>> And we'll put that into the chat before
the end of the meeting.
>> And then the final thing that our
committee has um jurisdiction over is
stability and readiness requirements.
recommend patient stability requirements
prior to psilocybin facilitation. So
that can include psychiatric and medical
stability thresholds and psychiatric and
medical clearance requirements. One of
the things I've seen um at least as a
warning on a lot of psilocybin things is
ensuring that electrolyte balances are
maintained. So that would be an example
of um a stability threshold. Are they um
their electrolytes balanced? What is
considered balanced to the board? Things
like that. Um last is membership.
Committee members shall be those
individuals who attend and participate
in the meeting. Members should reflect
relevant expertise including but not
limited to psychology, psychiatry,
psychology, medicine, nursing,
pharmarmacology, public health, living
experience where where appropriate. And
if you are disruptive during the
meeting, you may be removed. Don't come
cussing at me. Anyway,
for section 5.2 to pursuant to the
board, I was appointed as chair of this
committee. Um and then the duties of the
chair are just to convene and preside
over the meetings.
The meetings are going to be called um
as determined by the chair and directed
by the board to facilitate all of our
responsibilities before that um January
1st, 2027 deadline. um records and
reporting. We maintain minutes, records
of deliberations, written
recommendations, formal recommendations
um shall be transmitted to the board and
writing and entered into the official
record and the committee shall abide by
the American Nursing Association key
ethical principles of autonomy,
fidelity, justice, veracity,
beneficence, and non-maleficence,
which are basically just saying, let the
patient be autonomous. Don't lie to
them. Treat all patients equally. Tell
them the truth.
do good with what you practice and do no
harm. Um, and then amendments can be
amended by the board upon recommendation
of the committee and this will review
once the this will sunset once the
program is implemented and then further
qualifying conditions would just go
straight to the board.
Does anyone have any questions, comments
or concerns? I see Ann Met's hand
raised.
Yes. Um just a quick question. I know
the conflict of is uh conflict of
interest was an issue with the medical
psilocybin advisory board um for people
who might have financial interests um in
the program. Um you know my expectation
is that I will be eventually working in
this space. Um, and I wonder if that is
a conflict of interest and if I should
if it would be more appropriate to be a
non- voting member as a result or are
those conflicts of interest less
important to the committees?
>> The conflicts of interest are less
important to the committees. Basically,
what's going to happen is even if
there's a conflict of interest in the
committees, they will go be recommended
to the board which is free of conflicts
of interest. So it kind of balances
itself out, but it shouldn't be a
problem even if you want to participate
in the psilocybin program in the future.
>> Thank you.
>> Any other questions, comments, concerns,
discussion?
Uh, Gregory Evans.
Yeah, I just put this in the chat, but
um if there was some way that like the
people actively contributing to the
documentation could have like a shared
uh one note an chat that we can like
collaborate between meetings and um you
know
like if there's notes that I wanted to
add that could be reviewed by a
committee and however like you know it's
like I have some notes on qualifying
conditions and what we can look that
there like what's the best way to
approach that prior to something being p
actually published?
>> Uh Dominic, you have a good answer.
>> Yes, I do. So, thank you Greg. Uh the
issue with that is that everything that
we do and as far as the committees has
to be transparent and so uh the
unfortunate part is those kinds of uh
sites with the where you can actually
share documents like that end up
actually anybody can go in and make
changes on them. So if there are
specific documents to be reviewed they
can be sent to the program through the
email that we've posted um already as
far as for comments. uh they can be sent
to the here and we can present them uh
and then they can be you know
disseminated if necessary or posted up
on the website and then reviewed and
then decisions made at the next meeting.
The big thing to remember is uh that
again we everything that we do has to be
transparent and so that it's available
to individuals but we also want to make
sure that it's not just being changed by
anybody who is going in and potentially
changing or altering items without it
being reviewed. So we're happy to do
that. That's part of what the program
will do as far as getting documents out.
And then it's really up to this this
group as far as to make decisions and
when exactly to make those decisions.
>> If the so if the committee wants to
discuss something, we really should do
it during the course of a meeting and
not specifically like in between uh in
between sessions.
>> Correct. You have that correct. So that
got it. That way things are being done
transparently and open to the public.
Cool.
Thank you.
>> And and just so everybody knows, it may
seem and that sometimes that process
sometimes does slow it a little bit, but
we really want to make sure that things
are transparent and as accessible as
possible. So if there are items like
that, then again, we will share them as
best as we can.
>> Is it possible for you to paste the text
from this document into the chat so I
can make proper notes? Sure,
that'd be wonderful. Thank you.
>> Uh, I yield.
>> Right. And then James Brown
uh just one suggestion I had or just
comment was on the very first section
where we were talking about under the
purpose. Do we want to say anything
about harm reduction?
And also the other thing is is as we
begin this you know um it being medical
are we referring to everything as
medicine or substance? I think it's
important to kind of with that language
to make sure we are I don't know if we
want to be more broad in or more narrow
on our languaging. Uh just to make sure
we include everything like substances or
you know a lot of the training we heard
different wording or terminology used
besides just medicine. Uh I just didn't
know if that was a thought or an idea
that was those two things I had I yield.
So, I have personally no preference for
terminology.
I honestly just used medicine because
it's referred to within the medical
psilocybin program. So, I know for
federal reasons, we can't call it a
prescription and we can't um
we can call it a substance. That just
seems a little interesting. Um, kind of
sounds scary, but when you I have no
preference to how we do it. If you would
like to add harm reduction into the
purposes of the committee though, I
would have no objection to that.
And just as a note for everybody,
because this is the medical psilocybin
act, that is actually the other reason
why we utilize the term medicine because
the statute actually does confer it that
sort of um confer and utilize that
language with regard to the program.
And
>> can I make a motion then to uh
>> sorry
>> to get to get that harm reduction added
then if if the rest of the committee
members are in agreement to that or
um
go ahead and revise the purpose to
include um harm reduction and then we'll
vote on it as amended.
So, just as a question, there's a couple
places in this section that could be
added in. Where would you like it? Um,
James, do you have any particular uh
portion of it? I do have that part on
the screen right now for in the purpose.
Where would you like that included?
I have a question that is not related to
this but I do um support harm reduction
language within this documentation.
Um, personally I would put it with the
goal of protecting patient safety while
promoting equitable and effective access
to care and
ensuring adequate harm reduction.
>> Yeah, I think you're right, sir.
If I may, like are we I prefer I love
the term harm reduction, but are we
putting oursel at
potential scrutiny from those not in the
lexicon where they'll see the word harm
and assume that there is a great risk
that is maybe out of scope from the
reality? Is that like something we need
to be concerned about or is there
language public facing language that
could be better for that concept?
>> Tough question.
>> Don't have an answer. Given that the
medical cellment act that was passed
includes substance use disorder um
ensuring appropriate harm reduction
principles are applied I think would be
applicable there as we are just ensuring
that um if we are going to do harm
reduction that we are going to um
that there are conditions that qualify
right now that are doing great harm and
we're just trying to not necessarily
permanently fix all the damage But we're
reducing the harm that those drugs are
going to do by hopefully stopping the
addiction.
>> And I modified the language a little
bit. I did put it into the chat there so
that you can see uh if there's questions
on it.
And then James, you saw your high end
up. Did you have something else to add?
>> Yes. um do we have an established
frequency in which the committees will
be meeting on either a bi-weekly,
monthly or quarterly basis? So in my
head when I had originally um so right
now the bylaw say subject to the call of
the chair but um I was in my head
thinking about once a month that would
give us um time to a um get our
exclusion criteria, our safety criteria
and those kind of things knocked out of
the way pretty early, but then we can um
still have time to adequately react to
other committees. and board actions
because if for instance
we're setting up the qualifying
conditions, right, we have to report
that over to research and continuous
improvement so that they can know what
um conditions are we monitoring and how
are they efficacious and what is being
treated, what are the outcomes and that
kind of thing is going to be coming out
of that committee. So, um, it's just
about I don't want to do overly
burdensome often because it doesn't give
us the ability to see what kind of
happens with everything cuz there's a
lot of moving parts if that makes sense.
>> Okay. Thank you, Ian.
>> All right. With no other questions, I'll
entertain a motion to adopt the bylaws
as amended.
I'll second that motion.
>> I need one other person cuz I can't the
chair can't enter a motion,
>> right?
>> Can I make a motion to adopt the bylaws?
>> Okay, cool. And then do you still
second?
>> I I can also
>> Yes, I can second.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Um, if I can have the board
members who vote in favor of adopting
the bylaws please raise your hand on
teams.
>> Uh, just as a note in case anybody was
confused. I think Ian you mean committee
members. are those here and
participating.
>> Yeah. Yes. Anyone who introduced
themselves.
>> And do we need to publicly speak that,
Dominic, so that it reflects in the
record, the recorded record?
>> Yes. And so right now we have eight
voting in favor.
>> All right, we have eight in favor and
you can put your hands down. Is anyone
in objection?
Zero in objection. The bylaws are
passed.
>> Okay.
>> And we have one other business of the
day. Kind of brought it up a little bit
before which is just to define um the
legislative
conditions. So the legislature gave us
four qualifying conditions but did not
define them. So we need to just enter
them in as ICD10 codes and then
that should be what we have prepared for
today and we can move on to public
comment.
>> All right
>> Ian it should be showing now.
>> Yes. All right. So whereas the medical
psilocybin act establishes four initial
qualifying conditions for participation
in the medical psilocybin program PTSD,
substance use disorders, end of life and
MDD. We are going to go ahead and define
those and ICD10 codes because standard
practice within the US healthcare system
for clinical documentation, billing,
quality measurement, utiliz utilization
review and public health surveillance is
the use of ICD10 codes. So let us begin
with the first one. Treatment resistant
depression. I define that as major
depressive disorder uh F33.1 or F33.2
and documented failure of greater than
two anti-depressants.
PTSD that one was the most applicable to
ICD10 codes. It's just PTSD. PTSD the
code for PTSD. substance use disorders
um is alcohol, opiate, cannabis,
sedatives, cocaine, other stimulants,
nicotine, and other psychoactive
substance dependence. The only notable
exception from this one, if you follow
the ICD10 codes, is it skips F16, which
is um hallucinogen use disorder. I don't
believe that um there's evidence that
increased neuroplasticity will deter
hallucinogen use but
those are the defined ones that I
provided and then the last one end of
life related distress we put that as
palative of care status associated with
serious or lifelimiting illness and
ICD10 code for that.
All righty. Um, do we have any
questions, comments, concerns, and
discussion?
Uh, James Hass.
>> Yes, thank you. I'm just reading in the
medical conditions, uh, where it says
substance use disorders, and this is
just me being picky pharmacologically
speaking, but I think other stimulants
is a little redundant when we have
cocaine and nicotine a part of that uh,
>> stimulant drug class. So, I maybe I'm
just being too nitpicky here, but um it
seems a little bit redundant to add
cocaine, other stimulants, and nicotine
when they're all overencompassing.
I would agree. I believe I just entered
them because they are separate ICD10
codes, not because
I wanted redundance. Let me see.
And we can, just so everybody knows, we
can put this language uh if we need to.
You can leave the codes in as they are
and we can just take uh change it to um
uh just to say stimulants and take out
the cocaine and nicotine.
I would compare with that cuz F um 14.2
is cocaine dependence and then F15.2 is
other stimulant dependence. That's why
it's in there twice. It's not that I was
like, you know what?
Um
>> does nicotine not deserve its own? Like
smoking sensation is like a whole
industry.
>> Nicotine does have its own. That's
F17.2.
>> Got it. Cool.
>> Yeah. I don't know why ICD10 decided to
put cocaine and nicotine as separate but
then other stimulant. I don't know. I
wasn't on that board.
>> Maybe it's a large domestic hetamine.
>> Can't you do everything?
>> Yeah. Yeah. I would really recommend we
don't add every potential stimulant that
there is.
>> Let's list all the designer drugs.
Anybody have a copy of Tall?
Um
but yeah, so it changed to stimulants.
Cool. Uh Kate Hawk.
>> Yeah. on the uh end of life distress. I
know we're going to have more
discussions in the end of life care
committee and uh this is looks like a a
good starting place but I'm just
clarifying that you know this is our
thoughts for now and that there could be
more um discussion and modification on
this as we go.
>> Absolutely. Yeah. if we so these are
just the qualifying conditions that were
set forth by the legislature. Um so we
are 100% able to change them and make
modifications as necessary. Um the only
thing is that we have to you know
approve the additional conditions. These
are just kind of our our baseline um
place to start.
>> Right. Yeah. So, some of these things
like PTSD are um a really identifiable
disorder and end of life. You know,
there's a lot of different things that
go along with end of life distress that
maybe aren't in a really obvious
category. So, thank you.
>> Of course. And then Katherine Warup.
>> Yeah, I just wanted to kind of elaborate
a little bit more on that same topic. Um
there's a lot of discussion especially
um in the therapy um realm about people
that have end of life related distress
not associated with paliotative care um
you know there are people that are
crippled um for different reasons
usually extreme anxiety around death and
um I'm just was wondering if that's
something um it sounds like that might
be discussed more in the end of life
subcommittee but I just wanted to raise
that as a as an area for consideration.
>> Yeah. And I would have no like I would
not have put it as paliative care. It's
the closest ICD10 code to end of life
distress.
>> Um
it's
meant to be for paliotative care
associated with serious so like
life-threatening but also life limiting
illness. So if you one day wake up and
you need an amputation, that's going to
take an adjustment period. That's going
to take some grief. That's going to take
some um time to process. So I definitely
in my head included things like that.
However, um if you do not believe that
the language specifies enough, we can
definitely add language for end of life
because it's not my area of expertise.
Um, I definitely would defer to the end
of life committee, but um, if you do
think we need to add more now, we
definitely can. This is the first, you
know, draft of what we're what we're
defining those terms as.
All right. Any other discussion,
comments, questions, concerns?
Oh, Ian, there's a comment in uh the
chat. Um, and just to let you know that
yes, uh, additional Zcodes can be added,
but they have to be presented or I
should say conditions have to be
presented through petition process,
which has not yet been set up. That'll
be done as the regulations get uh,
actually approved. And this committee
actually is the one who will be setting
those sort of processes up if that makes
sense.
Did I plant a seed for failure to thrive
being I believe that's a condition.
Yeah,
>> that is a condition. Um
but it's a condition that could apply to
like
>> even a newborn can have failure to
thrive
>> like restrictions. But yeah,
>> so um with regard I considered failure
to thrive. My issue with failure to
thrive is that it's often used in by
providers as a catch-all. I don't know
what's going on. It's it
>> might open it might open too much like
uh
concern.
>> Yeah. I I I'm not trying to limit who
gets end of life related distress. they
are experiencing something that I cannot
fathom. So I definitely feel for them.
If there was a better ICD10 code that
kind of limited it to them more nicely,
I would pick it. I just haven't been
able to find one.
I if I may, what I would recommend is um
that the end of life committee
potentially as they get started with
their meetings that they um you know
think about how they they perceive that
and what areas might be covered and
maybe submit language to this committee
to say this is what we think it should
be. And remember these items can can be
adjusted. They are not uh the end- all
beall at this moment. This is the
starting point.
>> All right. And
you got
any other questions?
James,
>> again, I didn't know if ICD9 uh 10 code,
the F32.9
for MDD,
um I didn't know if that was looked at
or thought about.
I
um I would have no objection to
treating this, but it would have to come
through a um petition and add it as a
qualifying condition cuz F32.9
is for um a single episode of major
depressive disorder. And I don't know
how that would qualify as treatment
resistant if it was a single episode.
>> Sounds good.
All right.
So, does anyone want to move to adopt
these initial conditions?
>> I move to adopt these initial condition
conditions. This is Ann.
That's
>> I like the second, please.
>> James. Perfect. All those in favor,
please raise your hand
if you are in the committee.
Right.
Seven votes for yes.
And you can put your hand down. All
those against,
please raise your hand.
Okay,
one against.
The initial qualifying conditions are
passed. I will now turn over to the
Department of Health for public comment.
>> Okay. And uh just so everybody knows at
this time if anybody has public comment
um please go ahead and raise your hand
and we'll go ahead and start taking that
comment. If uh you are not able to speak
or you would like to present comment you
can either do so in the chat or as
mentioned and included in the chat
before and we'll repeat it here in just
a minute. you can send it to our uh
program email address by uh Monday,
January 5th, and we will include it in
with the minutes. Um, and so right now I
just see Kate Hawk, you have your hand
up.
Kate, you can unmute if you like.
>> Yeah, I'm I'm sorry. I just left that up
after voting. So, no comments.
Thank you, Kate.
Is there anybody who has additional
public comment?
Well, Ian, it does not appear. So, oh,
I'm sorry. There we go. We have Greg. Go
ahead, Greg.
>> I mean, I could talk all day.
Um, I do have a couple questions. Um,
they may be later things, but yeah. Um,
I think I understand the definition for
the submission process petition. We
email like our clear statement for
amendment and then review it on the next
committee. If I don't if there's
anything I'm missing there, please let
me know.
Um,
yeah,
>> you got that correct, Greg.
>> Cool. And then like I was really
interested and this this is going to be
a bigger conversation between the
committees on how we're h handling and
monitoring the dependencies with other
committees. Is that uh obligation for an
over steer from the DO specifically to
note like hey this needs to go to this
committee for review or this needs these
people should talk or is that uh
contained inside the responsibilities of
each committee to communicate with each
other.
Uh so that is an administrative
responsibility of the department Greg
and that's a part of why you see several
people here from the department in case
as we're actually um you know helping
with uh the meeting logistics if in case
one person misses something we have
someone else who can pick up on that. So
um but it is at the direction of the
committee. So, for example, with the um
with the end of life, that
recommendation on there, you know, we'll
make sure that that gets on over to the
end of life chair who is uh Dr. Larry
Leman. They are meeting just so
everybody knows next Thursday the 8th
from uh starting at 3:00. And so, we'll
be doing those.
>> And then I have one last thing. Um, is
there anything preventing the
broad collection of committee members
from collectively
brainstorming and communicating about
ideas to bring together to
for submission outside of these
meetings? Is there like can we all talk?
>> Yeah. any anything as far as that kind
of brainstorming or any of that should
actually happen during committee
meetings and that would be up to the
committee and to the chair to make that
determination of doing a brainstorm
session. Um, but it sounds like that's
something that you would kind of like
but again from a transparency standpoint
they really need to happen during the
meetings.
>> And then James,
>> thank you. Um question I had was on set
and setting with are is this committee
going to be addressing set and setting
or is that another committee down the
road? I I just wasn't sure because we
were doing the qualifications and stuff
but does that fall under us or
>> set and setting is under the dosage
administration and clinical practice
committee.
>> Great. Thank you.
And then Ian, just in case there are
people on the phone and can't see the
chat, I'd just like to say um Zack Snder
asked if they can get uh established
deadlines and when will the
subcommittees complete their roles in
the process. And the response on that is
each committee actually sets up their
meeting times and their deadlines. And
this is the first of those subcommittee
meetings. And so they are all starting
to have those uh here over the next week
or so or two weeks I believe. Um and
then we'll be working on that. Uh there
may not be established deadlines by the
end of the first meeting but I am sure
after the first couple of meetings for
each of these committees they will have
some deadlines put into place.
>> Yeah. And I already have um some
beginning work on like um exclusion
criteria and that kind of thing. Um I
can get those sent. We can't actually
discuss it, but I can say tear it up,
bring it to the next meeting um and we
can review it there and um yeah, that's
something that we can work on that way.
We are working
as a group, but we're not, you know,
having deliberations that would need to
be open to the public.
All righty. Well, if there is nothing
left, I
will adjourn.
Did you have anything else, Dominic?
>> Uh, just uh the only thing is I was just
able to put into chat again. If anybody
does have any additional written
comment, you can send them an email to
them to the medical.silicon
dooh.nm.gov.
We ask you do that by close of business
on Monday, January 5th, so we can
include it in all the documents uh and
get those uploaded hopefully by the end
of next week. But again, it does take a
few business days uh for um our system
to uh get items uploaded. So, just
please be patient with regard to that.
We will get them up as soon as possible.
And that's all. Back to you, Ian.
>> All righty. Um let's go ahead and
>> and just need to set the next uh
committee meeting.
>> Yes.
All right. Um,
would everyone be free
Friday the 13th of February?
>> Is that at 9:00 a.m.? Uh actually Ian
that is actually something that a
department of health would not be able
to do ourselves just on that particular
Friday. There is a another commitment
for a community meeting that we have not
a psilocybin one by the way everyone
just a different one uh actually related
to HIV and so none of our health
educators would be able to attend if we
were to do that date.
>> No worries. Uh would you be able to do
the 20th?
20th would work from Department of
Health standpoint.
>> Was that at 9:00 a.m.?
>> Yes.
>> Uh and just so everybody knows, uh the
legislative session ends on the 19th at
noon. So if we do it on the 20th, it
would also miss that.
Okay. And there's several people within
uh the chat that are saying the 20th
works.
>> All right. Well, with February 20th,
2026 at 9:00 a.m. being our next
meeting, I will go ahead and call this
one adjourned. The business of the day
was we passed our bylaws and we passed
our initial qualifying conditions.
You need anything else for me, Dominic?
>> No, not at this time. Thank you
everybody for being here and for a great
first committee meeting. And thank you,
Zach. Uh, thank you Ian rather. Sorry, I
was reading Zach's comment. Uh, thank
you Ian for uh chairing and we
appreciate it. And um again, we'll get
the documents up uh as soon as possible.
And yes, Katherine, from a public
standpoint, we do have to do the
registration each time just so that we
get the appropriate attendee list. Um so
we will be doing that once we get that
set up. We will send it out as we did in
these last ones through the constant
contact and it will get posted in the
announcement sections uh uh announcement
section. We are going to wait on posting
the next round of meetings until the
committees do all get a chance to meet
simply so we can reduce the amount of
email and um we will uh but once those
commi these committee meetings rather
meet, we'll get the meeting set up and
we'll send out another message similar
to what we did this time.
And yes, the meetings are recorded and
we will post the recordings up as soon
as possible as well.
Any other questions?
We'll try to answer them as best as we
can.
>> Is there like a best committee? Are we
going to have a little competition to
see who does the best work?
>> I'd be
>> I'll leave that I'll leave that to the
board.
Yeah. Yeah. Can we leave in a spot of
joy? This is really incredible. Ian
Dominic Jorge, everybody, thank you so
much.
>> Thank you all for being here and I hope
you have a wonderful 2026.
>> Happy New Year everybody.